Donald G. Adams Papers, Inclusive: 1962-1980, undated, Bulk: 1972-1977, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Donald G. Adams Papers
Inclusive: 1962-1980, undated, Bulk: 1972-1977, undated
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
33
Adams, Donald G., 1938 -
60 document boxes
The Donald G. Adams papers offer a glimpse into Adams's work as a Texas State Representative and Senator in Austin, spanning from 1962 to 1980. The collection is primarily comprised of legislation related to the congressional sessions Adams sat in and correspondence between Adams and constituents or Adams and other Texas politicians. In addition, the collection contains a mixture of books, pamphlets, clippings, campaign literature, and speech materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Donald G. Adams was born in 1938 in Jasper, Texas, to county judge T. Gilbert Adams and Dess Hart Adams. He attended Baylor University from 1957 to 1963, earning a Bachelor of Business Administration and a Bachelor of Laws. After his graduation, Adams took up legal practice in Lufkin for two years before returning to Jasper and forming a legal partnership with his father.
Adams announced his candidacy for the Texas House of Representatives in 1968. After his nomination by the Democratic Party, Adams was elected unopposed. As the Representative from District 7, Adams represented Hardin, Jasper, Newton, and Tyler counties. During his time in the Texas House, Adams served on several committees including Agriculture, Counties, Criminal Law, Criminal Jurisprudence, Insurance, Mental Health and Mental Retardation, Motor Transportation, and Imported Fire Ant Infestation. Adams largely avoided the political fallout that accompanied the Sharpstown Bank scandal that ensnared Governor Preston Smith, Lieutenant Governor Ben Barnes, and House Speaker Gus Mutscher.
In 1972, Adams announced his candidacy for the Texas Senate, District 3. Adams endured a slightly contentious primary battle with J.C. Stallings, a radio station owner from Nacogdoches who attempted to play up Adams’s connections to the ousted Mutscher and the Sharpstown scandal. Regardless, Adams received his party’s nomination and ran unopposed in the general election. Adams served in the Texas Senate from 1973 to 1977, representing Anderson, Angelina, Cherokee, Hardin, Henderson, Jasper, Kaufman, Nacogdoches, Newton, Panola, Rusk, Sabine, San Augustine, Shelby, and Tyler Counties. During his senatorial career, he was a member of the Administration, Finance, Intergovernmental Relations, and Jurisprudence Committees in addition to numerous subcommittees and temporary topical committees. In 1974, Adams served as a delegate to the Texas State Constitution Convention. In 1977, Adams was elected by the Senate as President Pro Tempore ad Interim for the 65th Legislature.
In 1978, Adams resigned from his Senate seat to become Chief Legal Counsel for the Governor of Texas. He was appointed to the Texas Industrial Commission (TIC) in October of the same year, was elected TIC Chairman in 1979, and was appointed to a full six-year term on the Commission in 1983.
Adams is also a member of various community organizations including Kiwanis Club, the Texas Bar Association, and Chamber of Commerce. Don and his wife, Linda Cullum Adams, have three children: Don Jr., Debra, and Dinah.
Scope and Content
The Donald G. Adams papers contain materials related to Adams’s political career in the Texas House of Representatives (61st and 62nd legislatures) and Texas Senate (63rd-65th legislatures). Included are correspondence between members of government and legislative constituents, copies of legislation, clippings, and campaign materials. Outlying materials provide additional context to Adams’s private life while working in state government.
Adams’s career coincided with a tumultuous series of events in Texas history. The Sharpstown Banking scandal became a salient issue in the 1972 election, leading to widespread disruption of the established legislative power structure and creating a more liberal legislature as many moderates became tarnished by their connections to this financial legislation/stock fraud scandal. Adams’s senate run skirted this issue fairly successfully despite his opponent J.C. Stallings’s consistent efforts to utilize the scandal against Adams in both print and radio advertisements. Stallings’s use of his personally-owned radio stations in the campaign became a part of the depiction of Stallings as an unscrupulous and litigious individual, which characterizes Adams’s approach to the issue. After defeating Stallings in the primary, Adams faced no opposition in the general election.
Adams’s Senate career also coincided with the Texas Constitutional Convention of 1974. Materials related to the Texas Constitution appear throughout Adams’s career. In addition to serving as an elected delegate at the convention, Adams proposed several amendments to the Constitution in the legislature and voted on other amendments introduced in legislative sessions. Along with constitutional amendments, Adams worked to amend the Texas Criminal Code and Family Code, especially as it related to parental rights of illegitimate children and foster families. In addition to these sweeping legislative issues, Adams was also a consistent advocate for both volunteer and professional firefighters, proposing legislation to improve their economic standing.
While in the legislature, Adams was a member of multiple committees and served as chairman of the Senate Administration Committee in the 64th and 65th sessions. Despite his varied and consistent committee membership, the only committees represented in this collection are the Administration, Jurisprudence, Intergovernmental Relations, and Counties Committees. Adams was a member of the House Counties Committee during the 62nd Legislature.
Adams diligently responded to constituent correspondence and appeared at community events when his schedule permitted it. This collection contains letters related to a broad range of legislative, community, and personal issues as well as a number of Adams’s responses.
Arrangement
The Adams papers were, for the most part, unprocessed prior to this latest round of processing. A preliminary inventory and folder listing had been prepared by staff in 1994.
Currently, the Adams papers are arranged into series according to topic and material type. There are six series altogether including I. Administrative, II. Campaigns, III. Committees,
IV. Correspondence, V. Legislative, and VI. Personal.
These series are divided even further into subseries. The divisions are based on legislative session, chronology, and topic and are further explained at the series level.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 33. Acquired 1980-12-29
Related Resources
Related collection materials
Lola Hopper collection #51
Related references
Kinch Jr., Sam. “Sharpstown Stock-Fraud Scandal.” Texas State Historical Association Handbook of Texas. Accessed August 7, 2019.
Legislative Reference Library of Texas. “Don Adams.” Accessed August 7, 2019.
Donald G. Adams papers, Accession #33, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Democratic Party (Tex.); Texas. Department of Parks and Wildlife.; Texas. Legislature. House of Representatives. Committee on County Affairs.; Texas. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Texas. Legislature. Senate. Committee on Administration.; Texas. Legislature. Senate. Committee on Intergovernmental Relations.; Texas. Legislature. Senate. Jurisprudence Committee.; Texas. Legislature. Senate.
Places
Texas -- Politics and government -- 1951-
Subjects
Adams, Donald G.; Agriculture -- Texas.; Education -- Texas.; Elections -- Texas.; Insurance -- State supervision -- Texas.; Judges -- Texas.; Labor -- Texas.; Law enforcement -- Texas -- History -- 20th century.; Political campaignsDLTexas--20th century.; Public health -- Texas.; Public utilities -- Texas.; Railroads -- Texas.; Transportation--Texas.; Universities and colleges -- Texas.; Water resources development -- Texas.
Genres
Advertisements.; Business correspondence.; Calendars.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Directories.; Legislative bills.; Personal correspondence.; Press releases.; Promotional materials.; Records (Documents); Resolutions (Law); Speeches.; Tracts (Ephemera)
- Administrative, 1962-1977, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. houses administrative material from Donald Adams, his campaigns, and his Texas House and Senate offices. The series is divided into three topics: District, Press, and General. This material includes various documents produced by Adams and his office to be circulated among his constituents and the press, as well as books and documents Adams collected to inform his political decision making.
  The District subseries contains documents relating to specific community issues within Adams’s senatorial district. Press contains press releases and directories. General contains miscellaneous materials pertaining to Adams’s time in the legislature including Capitol brochures, Adams’s calendars, and general committee assignments. Within each topic the materials are organized further by loose topics. The series is in good condition.
  - District Directory — Anderson-Henderson Counties, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - District Directory — Jasper-Rusk Counties, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - District Directory — Sabine-Tyler Counties, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Angelina and Cherokee County Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hardin County Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henderson County Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jasper County Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kaufman County Correspondence & Resource Directory, 1976-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nacogdoches & Panola County Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rusk County Correspondence and County Improvement Materials, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - San Augustine County Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Shelby County Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tyler County Correspondence, 1975-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Adams Newsletters, 1973-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Other Newsletters, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Angelina & Neches Scientific Area — Documents & Correspondence, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Appointments & Job Requests, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Councils of Governments, 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - District Democratic Primary Results [1 of 2], 1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - District Democratic Primary Results [2 of 2], 1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Employment Applications & Requests, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General District-Related Correspondence, 1975-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Supreme Court Records/Reports [1 of 2], 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Supreme Court Records/Reports [2 of 2], 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Government Reports, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Neches River Conservation District, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Rates & Correspondence, 1973-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pardons & Paroles Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Programs and Services of the Texas Industrial Commission, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Public & State Employee Salary Increases, 1973-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Radio and Television Station Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Regional Jail Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rusk County Savings & Loan Shareholders Directory, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sabine River Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stephen F. Austin State University Appropriations, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Toledo Bend Reservoir Park, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars Resolutions, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Wayne Sellars — Texas Railroad Board of Managers, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases & Related Documents, 1973-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Texas Association of Broadcasters Directory, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Comptroller of Public Accounts Biennial Revenue Estimate 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report of the Comptroller of Public Accounts Part 1B: Receipts and Disbursements of State Funds, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual Report of the Comptroller of Public Accounts Part 1A: Receipts and Disbursements of State Funds, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1972 Expense Reports — House (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 64th Legislature Committee Assignments, 1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - “A New Constitution for Texas: Text, Explanation, Commentary”, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Adams Calendars, 1970 June-December (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Adams House Expense Reports, 1969-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Adams House Expense Reports, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Audit Report — Parks & Wildlife Dept., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Campaign of 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Press Release — Campaign of 1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Constitutional Revision Convention Recommendations and Resolutions, 1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General Legislative Brochure, 1975-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlet on Competitive Insurance Rating, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Personnel Lists — Independent Bankers & Association Executives, 1972-1973, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Calendars, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Campaigns, 1968-1972, undated; 2
  Series II. contains materials related to and produced by Donald Adams's political campaigns. The series is split into two subseries based on the offices he campaigned for, State Representative and State Senator. The State Representative subseries includes correspondence related to the campaign, clippings, directories, and promotional materials. The State Senator subseries contains advertising correspondence, endorsement letters, campaign contributions, and papers related to the contentious 1972 Democratic Primary between Donald Adams and J.C. Stallings, a radio station owner from Nacogdoches. The materials within each subseries are organized by topic, and then alphabetically where appropriate. The series is in good condition.
  - State Representative, 1968-1970, undated; 1
    - Campaign Files and Directories, 1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Campaign Materials and Correspondence (1 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Materials and Correspondence (2 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Campaign-Related Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Other Campaigns' Materials, 1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - State Senator, 1970-1972, undated; 2
    - Adams Biography, 1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Endorsement Letters, 1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Announcements of Candidacy, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Campaign Issues, Clippings and Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Campaign Issues, Reports and Legislation, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Congratulations and Thank Yous, Democratic Primary, 1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - J.C. Stallings, Primary Opponent, 1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Radio Advertising Correspondence and Contracts, 1971-1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Advertising, Radio and Television, 1971-1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Campaign Advertising, Newspapers, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Campaign Advertising, General, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1972 Primary Results (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Television Advertising Correspondence and Contracts, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Campaign Clippings and Issues, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Campaign Contributions (1 of 2), 1971-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Campaign Contributions (2 of 2), 1971-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Candidate Filing Fees, Correspondence and Forms, 1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - County Election Results and Population Statistics, 1970-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General Campaign Files, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Committees, 1970-1977, undated; 3
  Series III. Committees is a collection of materials produced by Adams’s committee assignments. It is divided into four subseries covering the four major committees Adams served on: the Administration Committee, Counties Committee, Intergovernmental Relations Committee, and Jurisprudence Committee. The materials are organized within each subseries by topic.
  The series includes correspondence between Adams and other members of the various committees, legislation referred to the committees, and material about the various issues raised during Adams's time on these four committees. Of particular note, the Administration Committee subseries contains information about Don Yarbrough’s impeachment from the State Supreme Court. Overall, this series is in good condition.
  Access Restrictions
  All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
  - Administration Committee, 1973-1977, undated; 1
    - Correspondence, 1973-1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - HCR 3 and SCR 15, Rules for the 63rd Legislative Session, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Staff and Department Lists, 1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Administrative Committee Policy Manual, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Fiscal Accounting Reports, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Personnel and Financial Documents, 1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - SB 218, Organization of Senate and Committees, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Senate Office Space Request, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Personnel Job Applications, References, and Resignations, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Employee Insurance Correspondence, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Personnel Department Handbook/Procedures and Employee Retirement System, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Fiscal and Planning Reports and Vouchers (1 of 2), 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Fiscal and Planning Reports and Vouchers (2 of 2), 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Senate Personnel Payroll Data and Proposed Raises, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Committee Lists, Reports, and Studies, 1975-1976, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Senate Structure and Operations Reports, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Committee Minutes, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters, Reports, and Court Reports, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Committee Reports, 1976, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1976 Texas Constitution, Yarbrough Clippings, 1977, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Texas Legislative Council, "Actions and Papers Relative to the Address of the GovernorELfor the Removal from Office of Donald B. Yarbrough" (1 of 3), 1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Texas Legislative Council, "Actions and Papers Relative to the Address of the GovernorELfor the Removal from Office of Donald B. Yarbrough" (2 of 3), 1977 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Texas Legislative Council, "Actions and Papers Relative to the Address of the GovernorELfor the Removal from Office of Donald B. Yarbrough" (3 of 3), 1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Yarbrough Grand Jury Testimony, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Yarbrough and Rothkopf Conversation Transcripts (1 of 2), 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Yarbrough and Rothkopf Conversation Transcripts (2 of 2), 1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Adams’s Notes and Questions for Yarbrough Hearing, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - SCR 1 and HCR 2, Yarbrough Removal, Motions by Case Proponents and Respondents, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - SCR 3, Subpoenas and Correspondence, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Printouts of Case Law and Precedent with Adams’s Notes, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Yarbrough Investigation Documents, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Excerpts from Yarbrough Court Proceedings, Rothkopf Testimony, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Third Amended Original Formal Complaint, Motion to Disbar Yarbrough, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Yarbrough Restraining Order, Draft of Proponent’s Response to Objections, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Financial and Personnel Information, Case Law, and Reports (1 of 2), 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Financial and Personnel Information, Case Law, and Reports (2 of 2), 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Committee Report on the Meier Resolution of January 6, 1976, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Attorney General’s Investigation of the Secretary of the Senate, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Purchasing, Rental, and Inventory Policies (1 of 2), 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Purchasing, Rental, and Inventory Policies (2 of 2), 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Administrative Form Copies, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Administrative Equipment and Office Machine Information (1 of 2), 1975-1976, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Administrative Equipment and Office Machine Information (2 of 2), 1975-1976, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Counties Committee, 1971, undated; 2
    - Subcommittee on Salary Compensation, Bills, Correspondence, and Notes, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Committee Meetings and Bill Analyses, 1971, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Legislation Referred to Committee, House Bills (1 of 4), 1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Legislation Referred to Committee, House Bills (2 of 4), 1971 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Legislation Referred to Committee, House Bills (3 of 4), 1971 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Legislation Referred to Committee, House Bills (4 of 4), 1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Legislation Referred to Committee, Senate Bills, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - HB 384, Subcommittee on Salary Compensation, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Intergovernmental Relations Committee, 1973; 3
    - Committee Bills, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Jurisprudence Committee, 1970-1973, undated; 4
    - General Articles and Printed Case Law (1 of 2), 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - General Articles and Printed Case Law (2 of 2), 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - House Jurisprudence Committee, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Bills and Analyses, 63rd Legislature (1 of 3), 1973, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)